Mss.B.M82 Mss.B.M82
American Philosophical Society
John Morgan correspondence, 1763-1788
Mss.B.M82
American Philosophical Society
27.0 Item(s)
Nine of these letters are addressed to Sir Alexander Dick of Edinburgh (1763-1768), and relate to Morgan's medical studies, his travels on the Continent, and the founding of the medical department of the College of Physicians. These are copies of originals in possession of Mrs. Dick Cunyngham, Prestonfield House, Edinburgh. In addition there are letters from Morgan to: Petrus Camper, William Smith, Samuel Vaughan, Jr.; and from Peter Collinson to Camper; Camper to Morgan; S. Vaughan Jr. to Camper; and an exchange between Christian F. Michaelis and Camper. These concern Morgan, with mentions of fossils (mastodon bones in America), natural history, comments on Franklin, Jefferson, and Angelica Kauffmann. These are from originals in the P. Camper Papers, on deposit (1976) at the University of Amsterdam Library. These letters are individually indexed in the card catalog in the library.
27 photocopies.
Morgan, John,1735-1789.
Box 1
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented in part from Antonio Pace, 1963, and Whitfield Bell, Jr., 1976, and accessioned, 1963 (1963 2511ph).
Biographical/Historical note
John Morgan was a Philadelphia physician and teacher.
Existence and Location of Originals note
Originals in possession of Mrs. Dick Cunyngham, and in the P. Camper Papers, University of Amsterdam Library.
Early American History Note
The John Morgan Collection consists of photocopies of Morgan's correspondence, 1763-1768. Many of the letters discuss medicine and medical education.
Camper, Petrus, 1722-1789; College of Physicians of Philadelphia.; Collinson, Peter, 1694-1768; Dick, Alexander, Sir, 1703-1785; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; Kauffmann, Angelica, 1741-1807; Michaelis, Christian Friedrich, 1727-1804; Smith, William; Vaughan, Samuel, 1762-1827; Education; Educational Material; Europe -- Description and travel -- Early works to 1800.; Medicine; Medicine -- Study and teaching.; Natural History; Natural history.; Paleontology -- North America.; Science and Technology; Scientific Correspondence
- Papers
  - Series One: Letters to Sir Alexander Dick, 1763-1768; B M82.1; Morgan, John,1735-1789.
    Scope and Contents note
    Photostats of 9 A.L.S.'s Contents: Pairs, Nov. 1, 1763. 3p. and add. Paris, Feb. 20,1764 3p. and add. London, Nov. 10, 1764. 2p. and add. Rome, June 16, 1764. 4p. Morgan, J. to A. Dick London, Feb. 15, 1765. 2p. and add. London, Feb. 25, 1765. 4p., add. Phila., July 15, 1765. 3p. and add. Phila., Aug. 29,1766. 3p. and add. Phila., March 28, 1768. 3p. and add.
    From originals in Pierpont Morgan Library. Principally about medical affairs. Dr. Franklin is mentioned in letters of Feb. 20,1764;June 16, 1764; Feb. 25, 1765; and March 28, 1768. The A.P.S. is mentioned in letter of March 28, 1768.
    - Letter to Sir Alexander Dick, Preston Field near Edinburgh, November 1, 1763; B M82.1; Morgan, John, 1735-1789
      Paris, Photostat of A.L.S. 3p. and add., end. Friendly letter. Tells of his visit in France.
    - Letter to Sir Alexander Dick, February 20, 1764; B M82.1; Morgan, John, 1735-1789.
      Photostat of A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning medicine in France. Mentions B.Franklin.
    - Letter to [Sir Alexander Dick], June 16, 1764; B M82.1; Morgan, John, 1735-1789
      Rome, Photostat of A.L.S. 4p. News of his honors in France. Italy. Mentions B.Franklin.
    - Letter to Sir Alexander Dick, Edinburgh, November 10, 1764; B M82.1; Morgan, John, 1735-1789
      London, Photostat of A.L.S. 2p. and add. Friendly letter of his European trip.
    - Letter to Sir Alexander Dick, Edinburgh, February 15, 1765; B M82.1; Morgan, John, 1735-1789.
      London, Photostat of A.L.S. 2p. and add., end. Introduces two Philadelphians.
    - Letter to Sir Alexander Dick, Prestonfield, February 25, 1765; B M82.1; Morgan, John, 1735-1789
      London, Photostat of A.L.S. 4p., add. Concerning B.Franklin. Wishes to be a Fellow at Edinburgh. General news.
    - Letter to Sir Alexander Dick, Edinburgh, July 15, 1765; B M82.1; Morgan, John, 1735-1789.
      Philadelphia, Photostat of A.L.S. 3p. and add., end. Seeks to be a Fellow of Edinburgh. Teaches in college at Philadelphia.
    - Letter to Sir Alexander Dick, August 29, 1766; B M82.1; Morgan, John, 1735-1789
      Philadelphia, Photostat of A.L.S. 3p. and add. Mentions B.Franklin. Introduces Rush and Potts. Concerning his marriage.
    - Letter to Sir Alexander Dick, Edinburgh, March 28, 1768; B M82.1; Morgan, John, 1735-1789
      Philadelphia, Photostat of A.L.S. 3p. and add., end. Medical school. Mentions Rush. Gunpowder ingredients discovered. Sarah and Richard Bache's marriage. Concerning B.Franklin.
  - Series Two: General Correspondence, 1764-1788
    - Letter to W[illia]m Smith, Philadelphia, November 16, 1764; B M82.2; Morgan, John, 1735-1789.
      London, Photo.of A.L.S. 3p.,end.and add. (from original in Church Hist.Soc.,Austin, Texas.) His trip in Europe and desire to come home to Pennsylvania, with plans to do so. Presented by Antonio Pace; Dec.1963.
    - Letter to P[ieter] Camper, Leyden, February 23, 1749/1750; B M82.3; 11-3/4x7; Collinson, P[eter], 1694-1768.
      London, Photo.of A.L.S. 4p.,add. (from original in Petrus Camper Papers, K. Nederlandsche Maatschappij tot Bevordering der Geneeskunst, on deposit in University of Amsterdam Library.) Copies letter of J.Payne, in re shell fish in marble. Refers to earthquakes, Catesby, and Gronovius.
    - Letter to [Pieter Camper], August 16, 1784; B M82.3; 8-1/2x7; Michaelis, [Christian] F[riedrich], 1754-1814.
      Photo.of A.L.S. 4p. (from original in Petrus Camper papers, K.Nederlandsche Maatschappij tot Bevordering der Geneeskunst, on deposit in Univ. of Amsterdam Library.) Mammoth bone from Ohio. Fossil bones and their identify. Refers to the Royal Society.
    - Letter to [Pieter Camper], October 8-9, 1784; B M82.3; 8-1/2x7; Michaelis, [Christian] F[riedrich], 1754-1814.
      Cassal, Photo.of A.L.S. 4p. (from original in Petrus Camper Papers, K.Nederlandsche Maatschappij tot Bevordering der Geneeskunst, on deposit in Univ. of Amsterdam Library.) How to acquire fossil bones in the U.S. from Morgan and the Ohio. Scientific letter. Refers to Tenon.
    - Letter to Peter Camper, November 25, 1784; B M82.3; 8-1/2x7; Michaelis, [Christian Friedrich], 1754-1814.
      Cassel, Photo.of A.L.S. 3p.and add. (from original in Petrus Camper Papers, K.Nederlandsche Maatschappij tot Bevordering der Geneeskunst, on deposit in University of Amsterdam Library.) Purchase of Morgan's fossil bones. Identification of various fossil bones.
    - Letter to [Pieter Camper], September 20, 1785; B M82.3; 8-1/2x7; Michaelis, [Christian Friedrich], 1754-1814.
      Cassel, Photo.of A.L.S. 2p.,end. (from original in Petrus Camper Papers, K.Nederlandsche Maatschappij tot Bevordering der Geneeskunst, on deposit in University of Amsterdam Library.) Morgan will not sell fossil bones. War interferes with acquisition of fossils from Ohio.
    - Letter to John Morgan, Philadelphia, July 28, 1787; B M82.3; 10-1/2x6-3/4; [Camper, Pieter, 1722-1789.]
      The Hague, Photo.of A.L. 3p.,add.via Samuel, William and John Vaughan. Draft. (from original in Petrus Camper Papers, K.Nederlandsche Maatschappij tot Bevordering der Geneeskunst, on deposit in University of Amsterdam Library.) Offers to purchase fossil bone collection through Michaelis. Identifies some animals from fossils.
    - Letter to Petrus Camper, The Hague, August 21, 1787; B M82.3; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Vaughan, Samuel, 1762-1827.
      London, Photo.of A.L.S. 3p.and add. (from original in Petrus Camper Papers, K.Nederlandsche Maatschappij tot Bevordering der Geneeskunst, on deposit in Univ.of Amsterdam Library.) Forwards Morgan's letter. Flight of birds. Questions in natural history. Forwards Jefferson's Notes... Friendly letter.
    - Letter to Petrus Camper, Leeuwarden, December 6, 1787; B M82.3; 8-3/4x7; Morgan, John, 1735-1789.
      Philadelphia, Photo.of A.L.S. 5p.and add. (from original in P.Camper Papers,K.Nederlandsche Maatschappij tot Bevordering der Geneeskunst, on deposit in University of Amsterdam Library.) Will sell fossil bones, due to urging of S. Vaughan,Jr. Wishes publications on them for self and APS.Refers to B.Franklin.
    - Letter to [C.F. Michaelis?], February 6, 1788; B M82.3; 10-1/2x6-1/2; Camper, Petrus, 1722-1789
      The Hague, Photo.of A.L. 2p. Draft. (from original in Petrus Camper Papers, K.Nederlandsche Maatschappij tot Bevordering der Geneeskunst, on deposit in Univ. of Amsterdam Library). Concerning fossil bones from Morgan. Comments of Jefferson's work. Refers to APS. Experiments on air.
    - Letter to John Morgan, February 8, 1788; B M82.3; 10-1/2x6-1/2; [Camper, Pieter, 1722-1789.]
      The Hague, Photo.of A.L. 2p. Draft. (from P.Camper Papers, K.Nederlandsche Maatschappij tot Bevordering der Geneeskunst, on deposit in University of Amsterdam Library.) Payment for fossil bones. Thanks Vaughan. Natural history comments.
    - Letter to [Pieter] Camper, May 14, 1788; B M82.3; 9x7; Morgan, John, 1735-1789.
      Philadelphia, Photo.of A.L.S. 2p. (from original in Petrus Camper Papers, K.Nederlandsche Maatschappij tot Bevordering der Geneeskunst, on deposit in University of Amsterdam Library.) Received payment for fossils which will be shipped by Vaughan, as directed. Additional bones. Refers to Pennsylvania Hospital.
    - Letter to Peter Camper, June 30, 1788; B M82.3; 10-3/4x6-3/4; Morgan, John, 1735-1789.
      Philadelphia, Photo.of A.L.S. 1p. (from original in P.Camper Papers, K.Nederlandsche Maatschappij tot Bevordering der Geneeskunst, on deposit in University of Amsterdam Library.) Forwards fossils and bones to S.Vaughan, Jr. Lists contents of boxes.
    - Letter to [Pieter] Camper, Undated; B M82.3; 8-3/4x7; Vaughan, Samuel, 1762-1827.
      Monday evening. Photo.of A.L.S. 3p.and add. In French. (from original in P.Camper Papers, K. Nederlandsche Maatschappij tot Bevordering der Geneeskunst, on deposit in University of Amsterdam Library.) Concerning John Morgan and his fossils. Refers to the University of Pennsylvania, Angelica Kauffmann,etc.